A Guide to the Spotswood Garden Club Records, 1924-2018: SC 0146
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Spotswood Garden Club Records
1924-2018
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Spotswood Garden Club
SC 0146
3.47 cubic feet; 7 boxes
The Spotswood Garden Club Records, 1924-2018, are comprised of the administrative records of the club and include meeting minutes, files, and scrapbooks.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Acquisition Information
This collection was placed on deposit with Special Collections on September 10, 1997 by club representative Electra C. Julias. Additional donation of scrapbooks was made on July 23, 2018, by Sandra Hodge.
Administrative History
The Spotswood Garden Club was founded in Harrisonburg in 1924, with twenty-four charter members and Mrs. James C. Johnston as president. The goals of the club were "the culture and study of flowers, to aid in conservation of forests, native shrubs, wildflowers and birds, and to foster civic improvements." In 1929, the club was elected to membership in the Garden Club of Virginia, and has frequently participated in that organization's annual Historic Garden Week by securing the cooperation of owners of historic homes in the area to open those homes and grounds for public appreciation. Community work has been an important focus through the years. The club emphasized "Victory Gardens" during World War II and later worked for legislation to remove unsightly billboards. It has sponsored a variety of activities to enhance appreciation of native wildflowers, and has planted gardens at nursing homes, schools, hospitals, cemeteries, and throughout the city. Spotswood Garden Club has also sponsored or co-sponsored many flower shows. In 1983 the club undertook the restoration of the historic garden at Fort Harrison in Dayton, including its continuing maintenance. In 1991 the club joined Greener Harrisonburg and intensified its city beautification efforts.
Scope and Content
The Spotswood Garden Club Records, 1924-2018, are comprised of the administrative records of the club and include meeting minutes, files, and scrapbooks. Additonal materials include annual reports and flower show programs.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged by item type and further arranged chronologically.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Spotswood Garden Club (Harrisonburg, Va.); Gardens -- Virginia -- Harrisonburg; Flower gardening -- Virginia -- Harrisonburg -- Societies, etc; Flower arrangement -- Virginia -- Harrisonburg; Flower shows -- Virginia -- Harrisonburg; Victory gardens; World War, 1939-1945 -- Food supply; Historic gardens -- Virginia; Gardens -- Conservation and restoration; Fort Harrison (Va.); Harrisonburg (Va.) -- Societies, etc; Harrisonburg (Va.) -- Social life and customs; Harrisonburg (Va.) -- History -- Sources
- Minute Book No. 1, 1924 - 1926, 1928 - 1931 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Minute Book No. 1A, 1926 - 1927 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Minute Book No. 2, 1931 - 1935 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Minute Book No. 3, 1935 - 1940 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Minute Book No. 4, 1940 - 1946 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Minute Book No. 5, 1947 - 1949 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Minute Book No. 6, 1949 - 1952 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Minute Book No. 7, 1952 - 1954 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Minute Book No. 8, 1954 - 1957 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Minute Book No. 9, 1957 - 1960 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Minute Book No. 10, 1960 - 1968 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Minute Book No. 11, 1968 - 1977 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Minute Book No. 12, 1983 - 1990 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Minute Book No. 13, 1990 - 1995 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Minute Book No. 14, 1995 - 2001 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Minute Book, January 2002-June 2010 (Box 5)
- Minute Book, September 2010-June 2018 (Box 5)
- Garden Gossip, 1929-1939 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Scrapbook, 1925-1957 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Scrapbook, 1946-1953 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Scrapbook, 1948-1951 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Scrapbook, 1951-1955 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Scrapbook, 1954-1960 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Scrapbook, 1957-1966 (Box OV 1)
- Scrapbook, 1960-1970 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Scrapbook, 1960-1971 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Scrapbook, 1967-1982 (Box OV 1)
- Scrapbook, 1980-1987 (Box OV 2)
- Scrapbook, 1987-1992 (Box OV 2)
- Scrapbook, 1992-1994 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Scrapbook, 1994-1996 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Scrapbook, 1996-1998 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Annual Reports, 1926-1968 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Contracts, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Flower Show Programs, 1926-1949 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- History, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)